<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of the B. Virgin giving an account of the miracles ascrib'd to her by Romish writers : with the grounds of worship paid to her / by a lay hand.</title>
            <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1247A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209895</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11209895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46819</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46819)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:77)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of the B. Virgin giving an account of the miracles ascrib'd to her by Romish writers : with the grounds of worship paid to her / by a lay hand.</title>
                  <author>Fleetwood, William, 1656-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing, NUC pre-1956 imprints to William Fleetwood.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46819:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46819:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Life and Death OF THE B. VIRGIN: Giving an Account of the MIRACLES Aſcrib'd to Her by <hi>Romiſh Writers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH THE Grounds of the <hi>Worſhip</hi> paid to Her.</p>
            <p>By a Lay Hand.</p>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RICE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 7. 1687.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near Stationers-Hall, 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46819:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46819:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Life and Death</hi> OF THE Bleſſed Virgin.</head>
            <p>ALL the Service that is paid to the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, is founded (as they love to ſpeak) upon the greatneſſes of <hi>Mary, i. e.</hi> upon the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Privileges ſhe received from God in her <hi>Conception, Birth, Life, Death, Reſurrection,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Aſſumption.</hi> Of theſe her Greatneſſes we find no mention at all in Holy Scripture, and I am perſuaded there is ſome myſtery and ſecret reaſon of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the ſilence of the Evangeliſts, who tell us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Birth, the Life or death of the Mother of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhe appears but in four or five paſſages of the Goſpel, from the birth of our Saviour; and even ſome of them are ſuch, as make not much for her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46819:3"/> Such, for example, is that which happened at the Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> where undertaking to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Lord there was no more Wine left to entertain the Gueſts, ſhe receiv'd an Anſwer, to our thinking, very hard: <hi>Woman, what have I to do with thee? mine hour is not yet come.</hi> And like to this is that other paſſage of the Goſpel, where ſhe ſtood without with his Brethren, with purpoſe he ſhould come and ſpeak with her. But to thoſe who brought the Meſſage, he returned this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Who is my Mother, and who are my Brethren?</hi> and went not, that we know of. This does not very well agree with that profound Reſpect, and reverend manner of Deportment, with which (they ſay) he treats her now in Heaven. This ſilence of the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> proceeds, unqueſtionably, from the ſame reaſon, for which it pleaſed God to conceal the Body of <hi>Moſes</hi> heretofore; to wit, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> might not find it out, and make an Idol of it. So God was pleaſed the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> ſhould ſay no more of her, than was neceſſary to teach us the Myſtery of the <hi>Incarnation;</hi> that Men might not (with any ſhew of reaſon) Father on his word, thoſe horrible Superſtitions which he foreſaw and knew <hi>Papiſm</hi> and falſe Devotion, would one day introduce into the World.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> have got nothing by this their Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Birth, the Life and Death of <hi>Mary.</hi> We know them very well without their help. We have divined and diſcovered all. God knows how, indeed, but ſo it is, we have a compleat Hiſtory of the whole. 'Tis true, it is ſo fabulous, and in ſome places ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that even the Legends of <hi>Latona,</hi> Mother of <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi> or of <hi>Rhea,</hi> called the Mother of the Gods, cannot poſſibly be more. In the deſign of making her a Goddeſs, and allotting her a Worſhip, very near to that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46819:3"/> we pay to Jeſus Chriſt, there is nothing great and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in the Birth and Death of our Lord, the Son, that <hi>Papiſm</hi> has forgot to imitate and attribute to the Mother, excepting that they have not dared, as yet, to ſay, She was conceived of the Holy Ghoſt. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſee a ſhort Abridgment of this Legend, which the <hi>Greeks</hi> (who were always notable Men at Invention) firſt began, and to which the <hi>Latins</hi> (ſcorning to ſtay behind) put the finiſhing hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, we have happily learn'd, (but you muſt not ask me how, or from whom,) that the Father of the Bleſſed Virgin's Name was <hi>Joachim,</hi> who was of the Royal Line, her Mothers, <hi>Ann.</hi> Which <hi>Ann</hi> had two <note place="margin">Baronius in apparatu An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> Siſters, the one called <hi>Mary,</hi> and the other <hi>Soba,</hi> all three Daughters of <hi>Matan</hi> the Prieſt; for it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the Royal and the Prieſtly Line ſhould concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and meet in her, who was to bring forth him, who is our Prieſt and King. From <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s time, <hi>Joachim</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Haereſ. 78. 79.</note> and <hi>Ann,</hi> have gone for the Father and Mother of the Bleſſed Virgin: But Revelation (like a Snow-ball) ſtill goes on encreaſing, and we have found, ſince <hi>John Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi>'s <note place="margin">J. Damaſcen. l. 14. de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. fide. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> time, who lived in the Eighth Century, that this <hi>Joachim</hi> was the Son of one <hi>Barpanther,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Panther.</hi> 'Tis true, theſe Names are not uſually found among the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Genealogies, nor are of <hi>Hebrew</hi> extract; but what was that to <hi>John Damaſcene,</hi> who neither underſtood a word of <hi>Hebrew,</hi> nor thought himſelf oblig'd to ſuch exactneſs? We are alſo told, to <note place="margin">Niceph. <hi>lib. 2. cap.</hi> 3.</note> whom the Siſters of this <hi>Ann</hi> were married, and alſo what Children they had. <hi>Mary,</hi> the Eldeſt, was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Town of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and was the Mother of <hi>Salone</hi> the Midwife. <hi>Soba,</hi> that was the ſecond Siſter was the Mother of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Mother of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and Couſin German to the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46819:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aun,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Joachim,</hi> that was to be the Mother of the Mother of the Saviour of the World (the Mother, I ſay, of her that was to be called our Goddeſs, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemereſs, our Comfortreſs, (for ſtrange things, you know, muſt have ſtrange Names) our Advocate, our Refuge, the Salvation of Chriſtians, the Perfection of the Divinity &amp; Trinity) received all manner of Tokens of the future Greatneſs of the Child ſhe was to bring into the World. She was Barren many years after her Marriage, &amp; becauſe they could not find in whom the fault lay, they were both of them cruelly aſham'd; and the High Prieſt <hi>Iſachar</hi> rejected the Offerings of <hi>Joachim,</hi> as of a dry and curſed Tree, ſaying to him with Indignation, <hi>Curſed is every one that begetteth not a Male Child in Iſrael. Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> (that underſtood theſe things too well, not to know <note place="margin">Pſeudo-Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liod. &amp; Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</note> that no ſuch Man as. <hi>Iſachar</hi> was at that time High Prieſt, and that they did not uſe to reject the Offerings of ſuch Men as had barren Wives,) durſt not adopt this paſſage of the ſtory, although he does the reſt. But till his time, none ever dar'd to call this Hiſtory into queſtion, but it went for certain an undoubted truth, upon the pretended Authority of St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> They add farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that <hi>Joachim,</hi> covered with confuſion for the affront the High Prieſt had offered him, reſolved never to go home again; and that <hi>Ann,</hi> depriv'd of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her Husband, betook herſelf to her Prayers, that God would pleaſe to ſend him back, and to take away this her reproach. And hereupon it was, that <hi>Bernardin de</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mariate Part 2. Ser. 3. Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart. de Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſwar. in Stellario l. 1. part. 1. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Buſtis</hi> made that pious and ingenious Application of the words of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Joachim,</hi> and <hi>Ann. In the beginning God made Heaven and Earth:</hi> By Heaven (ſays he) we muſt underſtand the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Lady of the World. <hi>And God ſaid, Let there be Light:</hi> That is (ſays he) Let <hi>Mary</hi> be begotten, and be born. Poor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46819:4"/> 
               <hi>Joachim,</hi> overwhelm'd with grief, went and hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Wilderneſs, where continuing forty days in Prayer and Faſting, an Angel at laſt appeared to him, and promis'd him the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> giving him this for a Token, that in going home, he ſhould meet his Wife at a certain Gate of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> called the Gilded Gato. <hi>Ann</hi> at the ſame time pouring forth her Prayers and Tears, was got into the Holy of Holies, to get as near as ſhe could to the Throne of God. Indeed, no Woman yet had enter'd into that Sacred Place, and even among Men, it was the privilege of the High Prieſt alone to do it, and that but once a Year, on the great Feaſt of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiations.</hi> But what might not ſhee do, who was to be the Mother of the Virgin? And who ſhould have dar'd to ſhat the door againſt her? Hither then the Angel came, and declar'd to her the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> and order'd her to go and meet her Husband in ſuch a place: It was the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> that perform'd this Office, as <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din de Buſtis,</hi> and <hi>Batholomew</hi> of <hi>Piſa,</hi> Authors of ſovereign and unqueſtionable Authority, both aſſure us: Who add moreover, That he received this Commiſſion of God with Joy incredible; and that returning into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the whole Quire of Angels ſet themſelves to Dance and Sing for Joy, having learned of him the approaching Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> who was to be their Queen.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Virgin, and our Lord, are on the ſquare, each of their Births annunciated by an Angel. Her Conception, in the next place, was alike Miraculous; for, (beſides that <hi>Joachim</hi> and <hi>Ann,</hi> were both of them paſt the age of having Children) it was <hi>Immaculate,</hi> i. e. <hi>Mary</hi> alſo, as well as <hi>Jeſus,</hi> was Conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Original Sin. The Church knew nothing of this Myſtery, for Eleven or Twelve hundred Years, when certain lazy Canons of <hi>Lyons</hi> ſet themſelves to invent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46819:5"/> this Fancy, whom St. <hi>Bernard</hi> labour'd to Confound, <note place="margin">Ep. 174. ad Can. Lugd.</note> but without any great ſucceſs. The devotion to the Virgin daily increaſing, it was found very convenient She ſhould be exempted from the Law, common to all the Children of <hi>Adam.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, that all the Fathers, St. <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome, Remigius,</hi> and the reſt, were of another opinion, as <hi>Melchior Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the Learned Biſhop of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> proves, from their Citations: But we are to appeal, it ſeems, from them, as incompetent Judges in this Caſe, though their Authority be very good in any other. The Jeſuite <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Eq. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. cap. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſput. 51.</note> does all he can, to Invalidate their Teſtimony and Authority. He ſays, That Proofs drawn from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, are not altogether ſure: That the greateſt part of Fathers, cited againſt the Immaculate Conception, deſerve not to be heard; and that, at laſt however, God had not revealed all things to all Men: That the Fathers were Ignorant of this great truth, the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which was reſerved for theſe latter Ages of the World.</p>
            <p>This is no place to give you an account of the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bickerings there have been, upon this ſcore, for many Ages, and even in this of ours, between the <hi>Jacobins,</hi> and <hi>Cordeliers,</hi> i. e. <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans.</hi> The former maintaining, with <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> that the Virgin was conceived in Original Sin: The latter, with <hi>Scotus,</hi> that She was conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. And although the Popes have never formally and in expreſs words, decreed it to be an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> yet they have defined it as a <hi>Truth,</hi> which no Man can oppoſe without great Raſhneſs. And it had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> to Preach, deliver their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Teach in publick or private, directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any thing againſt the Immaculate Conception of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46819:5"/> the Virgin, ſince which the worſhip of Her has exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly encreaſed; every Body almoſt hath choſen Her for their Patroneſs, and whole Kingdoms have put themſelves into <hi>Her Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this a place to refute this Extravagance in, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it very well deſerves to be refuted, ſince it ſmells ſtrongly of Profaneneſs, in that it deprives our Saviour of the Honour and Advantage of having been the only <hi>One</hi> that was Conceived without Sin; and of being the Redeemer of the World without Exception. For if the Bleſſed Virgin was without both Actual, and Original Sin, I do not ſee how She ſtood in need of either Remiſſion, or Redemption, and She contributed nothing to Her ſelf, or to Her own Salvation, by bring ing Jeſus Chriſt into the World.</p>
            <p>We muſt not here forget, that <hi>Papiſm,</hi> agreable to the ſpirit of Error by which it ſtands, has not failed to heap Fable upon Fable, and to eſtabliſh this Immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Conception, by many a lying Miracle, and many a falſe Viſion. Saint <hi>Briget</hi> has defin'd this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie many a time and oft, and the Virgin Mother has revealed it to her frequently, that She was Conceived without Original Sin, and many Miracles have been wrought to that purpoſe. But that which is as pretty, is, that the <hi>Dominicans</hi> have alſo had their Saint and <note place="margin">5 Book. Rev. the 13. and Book 6. cap. 49. Tom. 2. O. puſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tract. 31. c. 5.</note> Propheteſs, to maintain She was conceived in Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sin, and that was <hi>Catharine</hi> of <hi>Siena,</hi> whoſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is upheld by Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> as much more Creditable than that of <hi>Briget;</hi> for that <hi>Catharine</hi> had been Canonized in due and formal manner, when there was a lawful Pope, and ſo acknowledged over all the World, whereas <hi>Briget</hi> was Canoniz'd by <hi>Benet</hi> the IX. <note place="margin">Plus the II.</note> in a time of Schiſm, when no body knew who was the true Pope, or whether there was any ſuch at all.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:46819:6"/>
            <p>The <hi>Dominicans</hi> not contented with St. <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Revelation, would alſo have ſome Miracles to eſtabliſh their Opinion on; and I believe there are few in the <note place="margin">1507.</note> World, that have not heard of the famous Hiſtory of the <hi>Dominicans</hi> of <hi>Bearn,</hi> (and here in <hi>England,</hi> by the name of the Hiſtory of <hi>Jetſer)</hi> who took upon them to prove by Miracles, the Conception of the Virgin, to have been in Sin, againſt the <hi>Cordeliers.</hi> Four of theſe Men, undertook to deceive and cheat a wretched ſimp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Novice of their Convent; and one of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him like a Spirit, telling him, that the Order of <hi>Dominicans</hi> was moſt unjuſtly hated, becauſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taught after St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was Conceived in Original Sin: but that their Enemies the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> were ſufficiently tormented in Purgatory, and eſpecially among the reſt, <hi>Alexand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> of <hi>Hales,</hi> and <hi>John Duns Scotus,</hi> for teaching the contrary: The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf in like manner appeared to him, (that is to ſay, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ryar in her Habit) and Imprinted on his Right Hand (by way of Viſion) one of the Wounds of our Lord, her Son, which the Monk (without a Viſion) did really and indeed feel, to his very great pain; and very well he might, for the Virgin-Monk had pierced his Hand through with a great Nail. But in wounding him She gave him ſome Lint, and Rags made of our Saviours Swadling-bands whilſt they abode in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and aſſured him from her own ſelf, that She was Born in Original Sin. But the Monks, not ſatisfied with this, gave to our young Novice, (who was indeed a very ſtupid Block-head) a mighty ſtrong ſleeping Potion, which deprived him of all manner of Senſe, and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in this Fit, imprinted other four Wounds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Feet, his Hand and Side, with <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> to imitate the Wounds of our Saviour, and the Marks of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46819:6"/> St. <hi>Francis.</hi> Being come to himſelf, they made him believe, he had been in an Extaſie, during which the Bleſſed Spirit had imprinted on him theſe four new Wounds. They gave him alſo very frequently ſtrange Drinks to make him Foam, and ſtruggle againſt Death, as Jeſus Chriſt had done before him. Hitherto the poor Wretch had never doubted of the truth of all this, but believed in good earneſt, that he had had true Viſions from Heaven, and Apparitions of the Virgin. But now at laſt, began to ſuſpect there muſt be ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, Witchcraft, and Illuſion in the caſe; and therefore (after he had been thus Martyr'd ſeveral Months) makes his eſcape from the Convent, to the Magiſtrates, where he diſcovered all the Myſtery. <hi>Langius</hi> a Monk, in his Chronicle, in the Year 1509. adds, That they made an Image of the Virgin, and fill'd the Head of it with ſome red Liquor, which diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Eyes, She was reputed thereby to weep Blood. They coloured alſo an Hoſt with Vermilion, and Fleſh-colour, as though it had been turned into Fleſh; and all this to perſuade the World, their Doctrine of the Conception, was true. Four of the <hi>Dominicans</hi> were hereupon ſeiſed, <hi>Francis Vulchi,</hi> that counterfeited the Spirit; <hi>Stephen Boltzhorſt</hi> Preacher, whoſe Office was to vent theſe Viſions in the Pulpit, with <hi>J. Vetter,</hi> Prior of the Houſe, and <hi>H. Stenieker,</hi> Receiver; who were all Burnt over againſt the Convent, in the Year aforeſaid. This Story did not ſerve a little, towards the diſabuſing of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> ſome time after, when they reform'd themſelves, in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>The Monks, to whom Heaven, in theſe latter days, revealed the notable Circumſtance of the Immaculate Conception, have alſo, by the ſame Spirit of Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, learnt the very day when it was. It was on the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46819:7"/> eighth of <hi>December,</hi> and She was brought forth the <note place="margin">Her Birth.</note> eighth of <hi>September</hi> following; this we know, becauſe we know what Age the Virgin was of when She lay Inn of our Saviour: And knowing preciſely the Year of our Lord, we know alſo the Year of his Mothers Birth. Not that the Goſpel ſays a letter of her Age, but that's all one. We have found it in <hi>Nicephorus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 2. ex Enodo Antiochedo.</note> 
               <hi>Calliſtus,</hi> an Author that may compare with any Legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary in the World, and who, by conſequence, ſhall have as much Credit as a true Evangeliſt. We have found, I ſay, in this Hiſtorian, that the Virgin was juſt Fifteen, when She brought forth Jeſus Chriſt. She was Born at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Joachims</hi> own Houſe, that ſtood pretty near to the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> of which St. <hi>John,</hi> in the <hi>5th.</hi> of his Goſpel makes mention. For ſo ſays our old Friend, <hi>J. Damaſcen,</hi> who was Sainted <note place="margin">L. 4. c. 5. de Orth. fide &amp; Orat. 1. de Nat. Virg.</note> for having been a Martyr for the Worſhip of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Images. Others (and <hi>Toſtatus</hi> for one, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.) ſay, She was Born at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> or <hi>Seppharo,</hi> Three Leagues from thence; but where ever it was, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the whole Univerſe was moved at it: The Angels (as they did ſome time after for the Son) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended in Troops from Heaven, chanting out Hymns, and moſt Melodious Songs, in honour of the Spouſe of their Eternal King. The little holy Maid her ſelf, (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the uſe of her Reaſon as ſoon as She was Born) found alſo mighty Conſolation, and exceeding great Pleaſure in it. And, which is a greater Wonder yet, <note place="margin">Pelbart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Stel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larium lib. 5. part. 1. art. 3.</note> this Heavenly Melody is every Year repeated, on the ſame day. And by this Muſick, the day of her Birth, which had long been undiſcovered, came to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to a very Contemplative Saint, who had heard this Muſick every <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> and wondered what the matter was; (as a Wiſer Man than he, might very
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46819:7"/> well do) and therefore on a time, in one of his Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Fits, begged of God, that he would reveal this matter to him; and was anſwered, that on this day, the Glorious Virgin was Born; and thus has the Mother gotten the ſtart of her Son. She was even with him, in having Armies of Coeleſtial Spirits to celebrate the day of her Birth; but this yearly Repetition of the Angels Harmony, has given Her the advantage: For I don't know any Book that ſays, they do as much for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be, ſome Devoto of the Virgin, jealous of the glory of his Queen, may find ſomething leſs in the Birth of <hi>Mary,</hi> than in that of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe he hears of no new Star, that accompanied her Birth, as one did his. But this only ſerves to betray his want of reading; for had he ſeen but one <hi>Theophilus,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hiſtorian (of whoſe Age and Authority, it would be to no purpoſe to inquire, for no body can give you an account, but however of very good Credit in this Caſe); he could have told him, that on the Birth-day of the Virgin, the Light of the Sun was doubled; that the Moon received ſuch an augmentation of Light, that ſhe ſeem'd almoſt to equalize the Sun, ſo that the little Cloud that is wont to obſcure her, diſappeared on the night of this Nativity; and round her Globe ſhone (as it were) a great Star, of an extraordinary Fire, and Luſtre.</p>
            <p>I think, this was another kind of Star, than that which appeared to the Wiſe Men in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> which ſeemed to be but a pittiful flying Meteor in the Air, in compariſon with this. An Angel gave the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> before the Child was born, and an Angel did as much for Her, and the name of <hi>Mary</hi> was of Heavens choyce; and it was alſo Myſtical as well as that of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46819:8"/> 
               <hi>Jeſus,</hi> for <hi>Mary,</hi> or <hi>Miriam,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Star of the Sea.</hi> Not that any <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Rabbi,</hi> how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſoever, ever underſtood this <hi>Etymology,</hi> but that it was revealed to our Legendaries ſo to ſignifie; that by vertue of it, ſhe might ſucceed to <hi>Venus,</hi> who was the Morning Star before, and Preſident of the Sea, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a kind of right thereto, by Her extraction from the <hi>Froth</hi> of it: For, as <hi>Salmeron</hi> the Jeſuite ſays, as <note place="margin">Tome 3. Tract. 4.</note> the Star that is called <hi>Heſperus,</hi> and <hi>Lucifer,</hi> directs and conducts the Sailers to the Port, ſo the Mother of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> ſuccours us in all our Dangers, that we may arrive at the Port of the Grace of God, and Life Eternal. Common Seamen have another kind of opinion of her Power, in reſpect of Ports and Havens, in this World too.</p>
            <p>After the Birth, next comes her Education in her <note place="margin">Niceph. l. 1. cap. 7. Damaſc. ubi ſupra. Cermanes Conſt. in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comio B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis.</note> tendereſt years, the Scriptures ſay nothing of this nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but we have loſt nothing by that, for we learn elſewhere. That <hi>Ann,</hi> to obtain her of God, had, as <hi>Hannah</hi> heretofore had done for <hi>Saemuel,</hi> vowed her to his Service: And that when ſhe was weaned and three Years old, ſhe was preſented to the High Prieſt, who received her as a precious Jewel, and Lodged her in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> where before ſtood the <hi>Ark of the Covenant,</hi> and where he himſelf alone had right to enter, once a Year. <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Father of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> was (it ſeems) High Prieſt, and made no ſuch unneceſſary Scruple as theſe, How ſhould I intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a little Girl, into a place where I my ſelf can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in but once a year? How can I, in the moſt ſacred and auguſt Partition of the Temple, bring in a Bed, a Nurſe, and little Child, with all that's neceſſary in ſuch a caſe? And what ſhall become of all the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities inſeparable from the Infant Age? But being a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46819:8"/> Prophet, and knowing the Myſtery of all, he received her without any ſtickling. Thither ſhe was brought accompanied with troops of Virgins with ſlaming Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in their hands, and there was brought up for eleven years, the Angels all the while ſupplying her with nouriſhment. After eleven years, the Prieſts aſſembled to conſult what they ſhould do with this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Virgin, and at laſt concluded, to commit her to the Guardianſhip of St. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> of whoſe vertue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence they were very well aſſured. 11 and 3 make 14, and at 14 ſhe was affianc'd to <hi>Joſeph;</hi> 3 months after, the Angel came with the Salutation, ſhe conceived of the Holy Ghoſt, and was brought to bed at 15.</p>
            <p>An unbelieving <hi>Jew,</hi> would make a great many odd exceptions to this Hiſtory, he would ſay it was a thing unheard of in the Myſtery of Religion, to introduce, to feed and bring up a Girl in the <hi>Holy of Holies,</hi> where ordinary Prieſts themſelves durſt never enter. He would tell us that Women, were they never ſo pure, were never admitted into the Temple beyond the place called the Womens Court. He would ſay, it was very ſtrange the <hi>Rabbins</hi> and ancient Doctors ſhould mention no ſuch thing as this, either to recount or refute it. He would add moreover, that in the Catalogue of High Prieſts, he could find no ſuch Man as <hi>Zachary,</hi> the Father of <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> Indeed, theſe difficulties have put our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <note place="margin">Coſterus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. 3. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Virg.</note> Doctors to no ſmall trouble; and now they rather chuſe to ſay, that round the Sanctuary there were little Chambers, where Recluſes and Religious Maids were bred up, and worked for the Temple, to whoſe care the Education of little <hi>Mary</hi> was intruſted: But our old devout Gentlemen heretofore, never concerned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with any Scruples or Objections of Unbelievers, but in great ſimplicity ſwallowed all for truth, upon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46819:9"/> word and authority of Saints, ſuch as <hi>J. Damaſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, and conſequently made Infallible, at leaſt by the tacit conſent of the Church. And who can forbear belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Hiſtory that has gotten ſome twelve hundred years upon his head? For <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> reports this: And <note place="margin">In Natalib. Chr. tom. 3.</note> though he reports it only as an <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Hiſtory, yet the Church has ſince made it as good as <hi>Canonical,</hi> by an univerſal Belief of it.</p>
            <p>The Bleſſed Virgin conſented to live with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in ſhew of Marriage, but in effect, in pure Virginity, for ſhe told him ſecretly, that ſhe had made a Vow of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, and withal advis'd him to do ſo too. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her Vow, which ſeem'd to determine her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to become a Mother, ſhe quickly after became ſo, by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt. And here, the Doctors are in great trouble to know, of what it was, that the Virgin conceived, and formed the Saviour of the World. Some believe the Holy Ghoſt took three drops of her Heart-blood, and diſpoſed them in their place, to make the Body of our Lord. <hi>Salmeron,</hi> though <note place="margin">Tome 3. tract. 9.</note> he reject this Opinion, yet allows it to be a devout reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Contemplation. But he himſelf is of another mind, which I cannot give you in his terms, no more than I can the Opinions of other Authors upon this Occaſion, becauſe they ſearch into the Myſteries of Generation ſo profoundly and exactly, and examin them in ſuch a groſs and naked manner, that even the chaſteſt and moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Tranſlation of their <hi>Latin</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> would not fail to wound (or at leaſt diſorder) our Imagination. It would be worſe yet, if I ſhould recite any thing out of a Book, that was current in the laſt Age, (and it may be, is in being now) intituled <hi>Proto Evangelium, ſive de Natalibus Chriſti, &amp; ipſius Matris V. Mariae,</hi> and Fathered on St. <hi>James.</hi> Here we may find enough to make the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46819:9"/> moſt ſhameleſs Proſtitutes to bluſh; upon occaſion of one <hi>Salome</hi> a Midwife, who would not believe a Virgin had brought forth, but would needs be as curious in her way, as St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> doubting of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was afterwards, in his. One <hi>William P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtell,</hi> in the preceeding Age, made the diſcovery of this Horrible Goſpel, God knows whence. But is it not a pretty ready way, to bring the True and Sacred Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt into contempt?</p>
            <p>I will paſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all the impertinent tales with which they cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Life of the Bleſſed Virgin. The care ſhe took <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> keep the Fore-skin of our Lord, at his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion. The pains ſhe was at to gather all the Blood and Water that fell from his hands, and feet, and ſide, upon the Croſs; and in particular, the care ſhe had to keep the Nails that ſaſtened him thereto. I will paſs over all this (I ſay) and a hundred ſuch like things, to come to the laſt and greateſt action of all, her <hi>Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> into Heaven, becauſe it is one of the principal Stories on whcih the Worſhip of the Bleſſed Virgin is eſtabliſh'd. Thus then the Gentlemen report the matter.</p>
            <p>The Bleſſed Virgin lived upon the Earth after her <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pelbart,</hi> who lived in the Year 1471. and dedicated his Book to Pope <hi>Sixt.</hi> IV.</note> Son, till ſhe was Fifty Eight years old, as ſome ſay; Sixty Three, as others; and others, more by a great deal. At laſt ſhe Prayed very earneſtly to her Son, that ſhe might depart from this place of Pilgrimage on Earth, and be gathered unto him; who thereupon ſent an Angel to her, promiſing that within three days he would take her to himſelf. Together with this News, the Angel delivered her a branch of Palm that he brought from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and told her, ſhe muſt have it carried before her Bier to her Interment; he gave her alſo a Suit of Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which her Son had ſent her. Of this Angel ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded two things; firſt, that ſhe might be buried by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46819:10"/> all the Apoſtles. Secondly, that when her Soul depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from her Body, it might meet with none of the Devils, or Malign Spirits. Upon which laſt demand, the Angel ſaid unto her, <hi>Madam, why are you afraid to meet the Devil, whoſe Head it is that you have bruiſed? However what you ask, you ſhall have: You ſhall meet with no Devils, and the Noble Apoſtles ſhall Inter you.</hi> Upon this the Angel re-aſcended into Heaven, environ'd with a great Light. And ſuddenly the branch of Palm that he had brought, and left in the Virgins hand, became exceeding bright, of a lively ſhining Green, and every leaf thereof as glorious as the Morning Star.</p>
            <p>To free you from all manner of doubt in this matter, St. <hi>Coſmus Veſtitor</hi> (from whom honeſt <hi>Pelbert</hi> ſays he took this Hiſtory,) tells us, he ſaw himſelf a little piece of this Branch, which retained to his days, a luſtre, equal to a very bright Star.</p>
            <p>The Virgin, full of Joy at this good news, aſſembled all the Virgins and Saints together, and gave them to underſtand her Death was now at hand, comforting them thereupon. At the ſame time was St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle Preaching at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and in the middle of his Sermon, comes me a clap of Thunder, and a white Cloud, that whisk'd him through the Air, and ſet him down at the Door of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> Houſe; where being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, he and the Virgin embrac'd each other, with abundance of Tears, and <hi>Mary</hi> recommended to his care, her Burial. At which words, the good Apoſtle threw himſelf down upon the Earth, and with a great deal of paſſion cry'd out and ſaid, <hi>Alas! My God, My God, Why doſt thou lay this ſore affliction upon us, to take away this Holy Miſtreſs of our Religion, the Mirror of Sanctity, and our only Conſolation?</hi> As he was thus lamenting, the Bleſſed Virgin ſhew'd him the ſhining Palm, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46819:10"/> Mourning Suit her Son had ſent her, and order'd him to take great care this Branch were carried before her Bier. St. <hi>John</hi> deſir'd with all his heart, that all the Apoſtles might accompany him at this Solemn Action, and immediately the Apoſtles, that were ſcattered in all the corners of the Earth, were carried through the Air on white Clouds, and ſet down before the Houſe, where entring in, and meeting with St. <hi>John,</hi> they were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly aſtoniſhed, but after Salutations, he explained the whole Myſtery to them, upon hearing of which, they were overwhelmed with grief, and entering into <hi>Maries</hi> room, adored her, in the Angels Salutation, ſaying <hi>Ave Maria, gratia plana, &amp;c.</hi> to whom the Virgin replied ſaying, <hi>God preſerve you, the choſen Diſciples of my only Son.</hi> After a great deal of homage &amp; adoration paid unto her by the Apoſtles, ſhe received the Communion, recommended her Spirit to her Son, kneeled down upon the ground, lift up her Soul to God, and diſpoſed herſelf to give up the ghoſt. About the third hour of the Night, Jeſus himſelf, with the nine Orders of Angels, the Aſſembly of Patriarchs, Prophets, Martyrs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Virgins, came down from Heaven, and ſtood about her Bed, the whole Coeleſtial Army ſinging Songs and admirable Hymns to the honour of <hi>Mary,</hi> Jeſus himſelf beginning, and ſaying, <hi>Come my choſen, come, and I will place Thee on my Throne.</hi> To whom the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin anſwered, <hi>Lo, I come, as it is written in the Volume of the Book, that I ſhould do thy will, O my God;</hi> and the reupon render'd up her Soul into the hands of her Son, who bore it away with him to Heaven. When the Soul was gone, the Body made ſhift of itſelf to ſay, <hi>I I give thee thanks, O Lord, for that I am thy glory; remem-Me, becauſe I am the work of thy hands, and have kept what you committed to my charge;</hi> upon which the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46819:11"/> ſo luminous, that the Maids who were preparing it for Burial, and could touch it very well before, could not ſo much as look upon it. Now when all things were ready, and the body to be taken up, the Apoſtles made abundance of Complements and Ceremonies, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Places of Honour to one another round, with great civility; but at laſt it was agreed, that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould carry the Corps, <hi>John</hi> ſhould go before with the Palm, and the reſt of the Apoſtles ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in couples. As they were going forward, Jeſus Chriſt march'd over them, with all his Angels, covered in a Cloud, and joyning Voices with the College of Apoſtles, they made an admirable Conſort; and at the ſame time, a moſt ſweet and fragrant Odour was ſpread through all the Region of the Air, on all hands.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> at this ſight, being fill'd with rage and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, thought this a very fair opportunity to rid their hands at once, of all the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt, there met together; and gathering together, the High Prieſt himſelf advances firſt, and moſt profanely lays his two hands upon the Bier, to ſtop them; when lo! imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately they both withered, and were torn of at the elbows, and there hung on each ſide of the Corps, whilſt the reſt that followed him, were ſtruck with blindneſs. The miſerable High Prieſt made a lamentable howling for the loſs of his hands, and for extreme anguiſh that he felt. But <hi>Peter</hi> told him honeſtly, there was no way to ſave himſelf, but by kiſſing the Bier where the Body of <hi>Mary</hi> lay, and making Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith, which he quickly did, and both his hands were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately faſtened on again. A little after, <hi>Peter</hi> gave him one of the Dates that grew on the Branch of Palm, to rubb his Followers eyes with, who thereupon reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their ſight. And now, without any further mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46819:11"/> they were come to the Vale of <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi> where they found a Sepulchre hewn out of a Rock, and altogether like that of Jeſus Chriſt; there they laid the Body of the Virgin, and continued three days in their Devotions at her Tomb. At the end of which, a bright Cloud ſhone all about the Sepulchre, the Voices of Angels ecchoed out from every quarter, a ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Savour was ſpread throughout the Air, and all the World was ſeiz'd with raviſhing aſtoniſhment. <hi>Jeſus</hi> deſcended with his Angels, and having ſaluted his Apoſtles, ſaid unto them, <hi>What Glory, and what Honour, think you, ought I to beſtow upon my Mother?</hi> To which, with one conſent, they anſwered, <hi>It ſeemeth juſt unto thy Servants, O Lord, that as Thou haſt vanquiſhed Death, and reigneſt from Generation to Generation, ſo alſo Thou ſhouldſt raiſe the Body of thy Mother, and ſet her at thy right hand for evermore.</hi> The Soul of <hi>Mary</hi> preſently appeared, and our Lord ſaid to it, <hi>Ariſe my well beloved, the Tabernacle of Glory, thou art fair, my dear beloved, and there is no blemiſh in thee; as thou haſt no ſpot, ſo ſhall thy Body never ſee corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus were things carried, according to the report of <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeſwar,</hi> a grave Author, whom Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> a Jeſuit, hath very lately cited abundance of <note place="margin">1 Part. tr. 1. quaeſt. 13. pag. 103.</note> times, (in his Book of <hi>True Devotion to the Virgin,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in 1679.) as worthy throughly to be believed; and <hi>Pelbart</hi> himſelf tells us, he had them from the Writings of St. <hi>Coſmus Veſtitor</hi> Othersreport theſe matters a little otherwiſe, in the buſineſs of the Virgins Tomb, which (they ſay) ſtood open three days, by reaſon St. <hi>Thomas</hi> was abſent, who earneſtly deſir'd (it would not be very fair to ask of whom he deſir'd this, or how he came to know ſhe was dead, but deſire he did,) the Conſolation of ſeeing the Body of <hi>Mary,</hi> which yet was not granted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46819:12"/> him, for he came, and found the Sepulchre was empty, and in the midſt of it, a Spring of <hi>Manna</hi> boyling up.</p>
            <p>O God! what face is this, to forge ſo ſilly a Romance, for which there is not in good Hiſtory, the leaſt foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? For in a word, in all this Rapſody, there's not a ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Truth: And yet this is the bottom of the Worſhip and Adoration paid to the Bleſſed Virgin, and of the Feaſt of her <hi>Aſſumption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not my buſineſs to confute this Story of the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> here; let it ſuffice, at preſent, that I adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you, it was unknown to all the Ancients for the firſt four Centuries. That paſſage in the Chronicle of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> is acknowledg'd by Men of Underſtanding, to be falſe and ſpurious; as likewiſe are the Pieces attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> together with the falſe <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> who wrote between Four and Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, at the ſooneſt. In a word, the Men of ſenſe and honeſty, even among the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> do at this day look upon the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> as an idle buſineſs, but I muſt not tell the People ſo. The Church of <hi>Paris</hi> ſeems to have declar'd openly againſt it; for by an Ordinance of the Cathedral Chapter of <hi>Noſtre Dame,</hi> the Firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1668, it was decreed, that ſuch a certain long Sermon, or Homily, that had been read in the Quire the firſt Canonical hour, for many years laſt paſt, on the Fifteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Feaſt of the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> every year, ſhould be read no more. (This Sermon, you muſt know, eſtabliſhed the Aſſumption both of Body and Soul, and was added by I can't tell who, from the Year 1549. or 1550.) and that henceforwards ſhould be read, what was uſually read out of the Martyrology, taken from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſwardus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46819:12"/>
            <p>Now the paſſage in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſwardus,</hi> which the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Who lived in the 9th. Cent.</note> and Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> ordered to be reſtored to its place, has theſe words: <hi>The Sleep or Death of</hi> Mary, <hi>the holy Mother of God.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">Although her Sacred Body is not found on Earth, yet the Church, who is a pious Mother, celebrates her bleſſed Memory, not doubting in the leaſt, but that She died according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all Mankind. But the Church being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate in her Judgments, hath rather choſen to own ſhe knows not where this Sacred Temple of the Holy Ghoſt is hidden by the Providence of God, than teach any thing herein either Vain or Apocryphal. Theſe</q> were the words, that were taken from the Service of the Feaſt of the Aſſumption, to thruſt in a certain Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that taught juſt contrary; ſaying, the Church look'd upon the Aſſumption of the Bleſſed Virgins body and ſoul into Heaven, as a thing very ſure and certain. <hi>Claudius Joly,</hi> Canon of the Church, and one of the <note place="margin">C. Joly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verbis Uſuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di diſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tatio J. Launoii de controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ſuper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribendo Martyrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio.</note> Commiſſaries, deputed to Examine this Affair, hath made a Diſſertation thereupon. And the Learned <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Launoy,</hi> has given his Judgment on the ſame Subject, in whoſe works one may find enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found this Story of the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> and anſwer <hi>Baronius</hi> and the reſt, who look upon it as a point of Faith, or at leaſt a Sacred Hiſtory, that no body muſt touch, or offer once to disbelieve.</p>
            <p>What we have hitherto ſeen of the Hiſtory of the Bleſſed Virgin, and on which the Worſhip that is paid to Her is founded, is but a little part of the Chronicle of the Mother of God. She has done more Miracles ſince her Death, than Jeſus Chriſt and all his Apoſtles did in all their Lives, in all the World; and we have huge great Volumes of them, ſome of which I cannot forbear giving you for a taſte, becauſe the Worſhip of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46819:13"/> the Bleſſed Virgin is exceedingly Built, and Eſtabliſhed on them, and becauſe they are at this day thought the efficacious and powerful Arguments to defend their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. And <hi>F. Craſſet,</hi> a Jeſuit of repute, thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo to be ſure, when in Anſwer to the Author of <hi>Sober advice to the Indiſcreet Devotos of the Virgin</hi>—He makes this Uſe of them.</p>
            <p>In the number of theſe Fables, I put the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Places of Devotion, where the Virgin is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly Worſhipped, where She works great Miracles, and whither Her Devotos go on Pilgrimage; the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I ſay of theſe Places, and their Holineſs, is found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſuch Fables, as I verily believe Pagans would bluſh to own. Such, for Example, is that on which is founded the famous Worſhip of our Lady of <hi>Mount Serrat.</hi> We are told, the firſt Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> had an exceeding handſome Daughter, but poſſeſſed with a Devil, whom the Count one day carried to a holy Man in the Neighbourhood, call'd Frier <hi>John Guerin,</hi> to the end he ſhould exorciſe the Devil, and deliver his Daughter: He did ſo, and for fear the Devil ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again into her, he adviſed the Count to leave her there ſome little time in his keeping; to which the Count conſented, and accordingly left her. Frier <hi>John</hi> being alone with this handſome young Lady, (and not being able to quell his own Devil) became enamoured of her; and in ſhort, Raviſh'd her firſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Kill'd her, at the inſtigation of a Devil diſguiſed like a Hermite. After this, being guilty of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Crimes, away he goes to <hi>Rome,</hi> there confeſſes himſelf to the Pope, who ordered him for Penance, to return to <hi>Mount Serrat</hi> upon all four, like a Beaſt as he was; and not to ſpeak a word, nor offer to get up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Legs, till a Child about three Months old ſhould
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46819:13"/> bid him riſe, and tell him God had pardoned his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Seven years after this, the Count of <hi>Barcelona</hi> was a Hunting, when ſome of his Men found out this Frier in a Den, all over hairy like a Bear, whom they took and Chained, and brought away with them to the Caſtle of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> where he was tied up in a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble like a Monſter. The Count a little after made a great Feaſt, and to divert his Company, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Monſter to be brought forth; whom as ſoon as the Earl's Child ſaw, that was there in its Nurſes Arms, it ſaid diſtinctly theſe words: <hi>Riſe up upon thy Feet, Frier</hi> John Guerin, <hi>for God hath pardoned thy Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> And immediately the Frier came to himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpeak, and tell the whole Story. Upon which the Count told him, that ſince God had pardoned him, he could do no leſs. But however, he deſired to know where he had buried his Daughter, that he might take up her Bones, and bury them in his Fathers Sepulchre. The good Frier conducted the Count's Servants to the place where he had Interr'd the Lady, and opening the Ground, they found her (Would you think it?) alive and well, as freſh, and as handſome as ever, excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a little kind of ſtreak like a Scarlet Thread, about her Neck, in the place where he had cut. The Maid ſpoke, and told them ſhe owed her Life to the Bleſſed Virgin, to whom ſhe had been Conſecrated, and who preſerved her (and indeed it was ſo) Miraculouſly. There they built a Convent, of which this young Lady was the <hi>Abbeſs,</hi> and Frier <hi>J. Guerin,</hi> the Confeſſor. Near to this place, in a certain Grotto, was found an <note place="margin">Ferreolus Locrius lib. 4. c. 25. Mariae Auguſtae.</note> Image of the Bleſſed Virgin, exceeding bright and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, and perfumed with excellent Sweets, which was diſcovered by Angels Melody, that were worſhip ping it in the Cave; this Image, they that found it,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46819:14"/> were for carrying away, but when they came as far as the place where the Lady had been buried, it grew ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy on their Hands, that they were glad to leave it there with all their Hearts. There they built a Chappel over it, although it was a very deſert place, and mighty incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the Pilgrims reſorting thither; and this is the riſe of that famous Chappel, where ſo many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and famous Things have been done.</p>
            <p>The Devotion of our Lady of <hi>Lieſſe,</hi> is founded on a Tale, no leſs ridiculous than the former, though it be ſomething leſs horrible. We are told, that a certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, Daughter to the <hi>Soldan</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the time of the Holy Wars, (the Original of all Romances) came to viſit three Gentlemen of <hi>Picardy,</hi> that were Priſoners at <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> and demanded of them the Picture of the Bleſſed Virgin. Not a Man of them underſtood a bit of Painting, but however one of them promiſed her Highneſs what ſhe required; but being put very hard to fulfil it, the Virgin delivered them from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, by giving them her Picture from Heaven her ſelf. The Princeſs upon this, found means to break their Priſon, and eſcape with them, and paſſing an arm of the Sea, they laid them down to ſleep in a Wood, and waking in the Morning, found themſelves in <hi>Picardy</hi> by a Fountain, where they built the Church of our Lady of <hi>Lieſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of this kind, there is nothing in the World more Renowned, and at the ſame time more Abſurd, than the Hiſtory of the famous Chamber of our Lady of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retto.</hi> This is the very Chamber of the Houſe of <hi>Joa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim</hi> and <hi>Ann,</hi> in the City of <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> in which the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was Born. (Our Legendaries ſhould conſult with one another, ſometimes, for before we heard She was Born in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with a great deal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46819:14"/> of Punctuality.) In this Chamber She received the Salutation of the Angel, in this Conceived the Saviour of the World, and in this bred Him up till He was Twelve Years of Age. The Apoſtles, after the Death of Jeſus Chriſt, obſerving carefully what a world of Miracles were wrought in this Chamber, judged it very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to build a Chappel there, and Celebrate the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries in it, that is to ſay, to ſing Maſs in it; and Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangeliſt, who was as good a Painter as Phyſician, drew with his own hand the Picture of the Virgin, which is there to be ſeen to this day. This Chappel was frequented with a great deal of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whilſt the Chriſtians ſtaid in <hi>Galilee,</hi> and eſpecially in the time of the <hi>Croiſades,</hi> or holy Wars, but the Chriſtians being chaſed away, and the Devotion at this Chamber beginning to cool apace, the Angels took it on the <hi>9th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> in the year, 1291. (ſays <hi>Turſelin,</hi> very exactly) and brought it through the Air into <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> diſtant from <hi>Galilee</hi> about Six thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miles; as thoſe who have caſt it up tell us, upon whom let it reſt. There the Angels ſet the Chamber or Chappel down upon a Hill, in view of the <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Sea, between two Towns, the one called <hi>Terſactum,</hi> and the other <hi>Flumen.</hi> At the firſt, there was a mighty concourſe of devout People, that came upon the fame of this great Miracle, but their Zeal continued not; and the Virgin not finding there, the honour ſhe expected, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Angels a ſecond time to take the Room, and paſſing the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea, to Tranſport it into <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſet it down in the Territory of <hi>Recanati,</hi> in the midſt of a Wood, belonging to a certain Lad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> (for without a Woman in the caſe, there can be no great Miracle) called <hi>Loretta,</hi> that owed the Dioceſs, or Territory of <hi>Recanati;</hi> which accordingly they did.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46819:15"/> This new Miracle of the ſecond Tranſportation of the Chamber, rekindled Mens devotion for the Virgin, and there was old flocking to it from all Quarters, but the Situation of the Chappel was an occaſion of a great many Robberies and Villanies committed on the poor Pilgrims, by reaſon that the Woods afforded ſhelter to the Rogues, who upon all occaſions Sallied out upon them, and retir'd into the ſame ſecurely. The Angels therefore thought it fit, it ſhould be taken from amidſt this Wood, and removed a little farther, to a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that belonged to two Brothers; which Brothers in a ſhort time, made a very profitable buſineſs of it, by the great reſort of Pilgrims, and the rich Preſents that were made, but not being able to agree in the diviſion of the Spoil, the Virgin was very angry, and thought they were unworthy of the honour She had done them, and therefore ordered the Angels to transfer it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place; up then they took it the fourth time, and ſet it in the High-way, where now it ſtands and works ſuch Miracles. The People of <hi>Recanati</hi> came to ſee this Miraculous Room, and finding it ſet upon the Ground without any manner of Foundation, were greatly afraid it would fall down, and therefore built about it a huge and mighty thick Wall, which ſtands at this preſent to be ſeen. But no body could tell from whence this Houſe came, till a long time after, when the Bleſſed Virgin appeared in a Dream to a certain Man, an intimate Friend and Servant of Hers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed the whole matter to him, as I have been rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it. This Man declared the ſame to a certain Wiſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderſtanding Perſon of that Country, who thought it convenient, to depute ſixteen Grave and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable Men, to go to <hi>Nazareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> and take Cognizance of the matter of Fact. Away they went,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46819:15"/> taking the Meaſure of the Houſe at <hi>Loretto</hi> with them, and came ſafe to <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where they found an empty ſpace, where the Virgins Houſe had ſtood, and nothing left but the Foundations, of which theſe Sixteen took the Length and Breadth, and finding them to agree moſt exactly with the Dimenſions of <hi>Loretto Houſe,</hi> they were ſufficiently convinced; but beſides, they found an Inſcription on the Wall hard by, atteſting that ſuch a Church had ſtood there heretofore, and was Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly carried away. And thus this truth was laid open as manifeſt as the Light, by the Teſtimony of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Jury and half of able Ambaſſadors, and this we find written in the Regiſters of that Houſe, and hung up in a Table in the Chappel, to be ſeen by all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. This is in effect, an <hi>Epitome</hi> of <hi>Turſellin</hi>'s great <note place="margin">Turſellin's Hiſtoriae Lauretanae, lib. 1.</note> Hiſtory of this Houſe, who ampliſies the Matter very curiouſly. This Jeſuit's Book was Printed with Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge from Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the VIII, with the general Approbation of the greateſt Doctors at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Raynaud, Bzovius, Spondanus,</hi> and others, who refer us to this Book as a Piece, that is able to eaſe us of all manner of Doubts, that may riſe on this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And will the time then never come, when Men will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume that Shame they have ſo long renounc'd? How is it poſſible they can in Earneſt, propagate ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences as this? <hi>Cui bono,</hi> To what end and purpoſe is it, that a Houſe muſt jump from place to place thus through the Air? Who does not ſee that this is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of one who is not the Father of Truth, to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thoſe lamentable Superſtitions, of which that Bleſſed Maid is made the Object?</p>
            <p>It may be convenient here to obſerve, that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Tranſportation is ſaid to have been made, at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46819:16"/> end of the Thirteenth Century, when the <hi>Saracens</hi> had entirely chaſed the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> out of <hi>Paleſtin:</hi> And yet St. <hi>Antonine,</hi> A. B. of <hi>Florence,</hi> one of the hardieſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, and greateſt Admirers of Fabulous Miracles, and ſtrange things, that perhaps the World ever had, ſays not one word of this Matter; and yet he ſhould have known, being an <hi>Italian,</hi> and living within 150. years of the time aſſigned for this great Wonder, and one that would have believed it, if he had but once heard on't. Another Saint alſo of the ſame Order, (a <hi>Dominican)</hi> and ſame Country, to wit, <hi>Vincent Ferrier,</hi> that lived according to <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Account, 1410. or as others ſay, in 1440. in a Sermon (amongſt his Works) on the Feaſt of the <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> ſays expreſsly, that our Ladies Chamber is ſtill at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and yet according to the Hiſtory, it had been then in <hi>Italy,</hi> above 100. years; And was it not poſſible that great Saint ſhould not know as much? But thus it is, The Fable was at firſt invented without any Conſcience, without any Shame, or indeed, without any Diſcretion; God ſo permitting it, for the farther evidencing this great Truth, that we might more eaſily ſee on what grounds all this kind of Worſhip is founded. But now for a Sample or two of Miracles.</p>
            <p>We are not to doubt, but as She is the moſt Glorious, She is alſo the moſt Holy, and by conſequence, the humbleſt of all Women. But <hi>Papiſm</hi> has made Her a very pattern of Pride and Ambition, always aiming at Divine Honours; angry with all that pay them not, ſeverely Puniſhing thoſe that offend Her, and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing amply all that are peculiarly devoted to Her, and working Miracles perpetually, for nothing but to acquire Adoration, and Honour to Her ſelf. To eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this Adoration, they have made ſuch a Romance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46819:16"/> of the Bleſſed Virgin, that no good ſober Heathen would have done the like to his <hi>Minerva</hi> or <hi>Diana,</hi> Goddeſſes of Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>For Example. What more could any Servant of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> or of <hi>Flora,</hi> Goddeſſes of Proſtitution, ſay of their Deities, than has been ſaid of <hi>Mary,</hi> when they make her marry St. <hi>Dominick.</hi> This Saint was in a Cavern, where he was doing Penances, alas! for the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> covered with gore and wounds of his own inflicting. To him the Virgin appeared, accompanied with three Women, each of them being attended with fifty other Women; theſe were (Oh horror to relate!) this three Perſons of the Holy Trinity, that made up <note place="margin">Alanus redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivus p. 2. c. 3.</note> the Nuptial Equipage and Pomp, when the Virgin was to marry <hi>Dominick;</hi> and coming to him, <hi>Dominick</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>my Son, my dear Husband, becauſe thou haſt valiantly fought againſt the Enemies of the Faith, lo I am come to ſuccour thee, I, (I ſay) whom thou ſo oft has call'd upon.</hi> Then the three Queens that accompanied her, lift up St. <hi>Dominick</hi> from the ground, where he lay half dead, and the Virgin received him into her embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, kiſſing him lovingly and tenderly, and withal opened her breaſts and let him ſuck, till he was perfectly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. In what a hot and furious imagination was the impudent Monk, think you, when he wrote theſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things? Came he not reeking from his damn'd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches, to commit theſe foul impurities to paper? I appeal to all Perſons in the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, of pious Minds and chaſt Thoughts, nay, to all the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Bleſſed Virgin, that have any ſenſe of Vertue, any touch of ſhame, to all ſuch I appeal for my juſt indignation againſt this. <hi>Alanus de Rupibus,</hi> (for he it is that reports theſe things, and that writes of the like abominable intercourſe betwixt the Virgin
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46819:17"/> and himſelf ſays, he was uſually tempted of the Devil, once in every ſeven years, and in one of theſe fits, he had like to have cut his own Throat for <note place="margin">Idem ibid. part 2. e. 4.</note> deſpair; but at Mid-night the Virgin came into his Cell, and after a great deal of diſcourſe, drew out her Breaſts, and milk'd them on the wounds the Devil had made, and cured them perfectly. Afterwards ſhe married her Servant in the preſence of Jeſus Chriſt, and a great many Saints there preſent, giving him her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Ring, made of her Virgin-hair. After this, ſhe put about his neck a Chain or String, made likewiſe of her hair, with a hundred and fifty Precious-ſtones, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of Beads in the Virgins <hi>Pſalter</hi> or <hi>Chaplet.</hi> After, ſhe gave him a ſweet Kiſs, and let him ſuck her Virgin-Breaſts, which he doing very greedily, ſeemed to have all his Body bedewed with a ſweet Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor; and this favour, he ſays, ſhe afforded him fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently. Another Story tells us, that one <hi>Euſtochium</hi> a Religious Nun, having begg'd of the Virgin to ſee the Child Jeſus, ſhe found him laid upon the ſtraw, where ſhe fell to kiſſing and embracing him ſo ardently, that ſhe thought ſhe ſhould have died for pleaſure, on the place. Another young Maid, about Fourteen, a devout Servant of the Virgins, having ask'd the ſame thing, <hi>Mary</hi> gave him into her arms, who embrac'd, careſs'd and kiſs'd him with ſuch violent tranſports of love, that her very heart was cleft aſunder. Fair warning, one would think, to young Maids!</p>
            <p>Has either <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh Talmud,</hi> Stories ſo lewd and ſo abominable as theſe? Yet theſe are the Authors, whoſe Authority <hi>F. Craſſet</hi> has within theſe ſix laſt years, renewed and re-eſtabliſhed in his Book! But what is the deſign of theſe tales? Why, 'tis to eſtabliſh the Worſhip of the Bleſſed Virgin; for St. <hi>Dominick</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46819:17"/> been her Husband, but that he invented the <hi>Roſary,</hi> otherwiſe call'd the <hi>Virgins Pſalter,</hi> compos'd of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Beads, of which there are fifteen <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> for God, (and well they can ſpare them too,) and and one hundred thirty five <hi>Ave Maria's</hi> for the Virgin. And for the ſame reaſon was our Friend <hi>Alan</hi> favoured, becauſe the Roſary-way of Worſhip beginning to decay, he did what in him lay to revive it. And for the two Virgins obtaining the favour to Kiſs Jeſus Chriſt in the Fleſh, even to Swooning away, why was it, but becauſe they were devoted to the Service of the Virgin in a more peculiar manner? Now, that you may not think theſe fearful Examples are but few in number, you muſt know there are abundance of them in all the Authors that <hi>F. Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> quotes and admires. <hi>Hautin,</hi> a Jeſuit like himſelf, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a Hiſtory from <hi>Surius,</hi> of the Marriage of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> with one <hi>Herman,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Joſeph,</hi> (becauſe they were both of them married to the Virgin,) to whom the Virgin came, accompanied with two Angels, one of which began to ſpeak and ſay, <hi>To whom ſhall we marry this Young Man?</hi> To <hi>Mary,</hi> replied the other, at which they commanded <hi>Herman</hi> to draw near: Poor <hi>Herman</hi> knew not what in the earth to do; Love prick'd him on, and Shame-fac'dneſs pull'd him back; for though before times he had had particular intimacy with the <note place="margin">Hautin An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus Cuſtos c. 4. numb. 3.</note> Bleſſed Virgin, yet he could never hope to ſee himſelf advanc'd to ſuch a degree, as to be married to Her. <hi>Caeſarius</hi> alſo, whom <hi>F. Craſſet</hi> quotes as a very ſincere <note place="margin">Caeſarius l. 7. c. 13, 18, 32, 52.</note> Author, relates the Story of a Soldier that fell in love with his Captain's Wife, and following the advice of a good Hermit, ſaluted the Virgin a hundred times a day, who to recompence this civility, offered herſelf to him like an exceeding handſom Woman, ſaying, <hi>I will be thy Wife, come kiſs me,</hi> and forc'd him to it. In the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46819:18"/> ſame Author, we find the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> kiſſing and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing Monks very liberally: Some ſhe watches over whilſt they ſleep; others ſhe wipes the face of, whilſt they ſleep, with her Handkerchief. And had I not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſay the Chronicles of <hi>Diana</hi> and <hi>Minerva</hi> were more chaſtly deliver'd down, than thoſe of the ever Bleſſed Mother of our Lord?</p>
            <p>After theſe favours, it would be vain to produce any more, or others; but you may be aſſured there is no ſort or kind, with which the <hi>Devoto's</hi> to the Virgin have not ſome time or other been graced. She has kept them in their Sickneſſes; She has given them their Sight; She has delivered them from extreme dangers both by Sea and Land, from Thieves, from Fire, from the Gibbet, from Priſons, and from Death itſelf; for many have been raiſed from the dead, only becauſe they or their Parents have been religious Worſhippers of the Bleſſed Virgin. Read but <hi>Chroni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on S. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. Deiparae,</hi> where you ſhall find a thouſand Inſtances. If one ſhould collect together all the deliverances God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th wrought from the beginning of the World, to this day, they would not make a Hiſtory to compare with thoſe wrought by our Lady of <hi>Loretto, Mont Serrat, Lieſſe, Hall, Moyenpont, Aſpremont, Ardiliers,</hi> and a hundred more, and all to perſuade Us, that the Virgin is mightily pleaſed to ſee Herſelf adored, and that ſhe is at a ſtand ſometimes to find out what Favours to beſtow on her peculiar Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>But that which is moſt abominable, is, that theſe Fables would perſuade Us, that the Service of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin is of greater benefit to Us, than that of God; and that, provided a Man dedicate himſelf to Her Service, let him be otherwiſe never ſo wicked a Villain, yet he need not deſpair of his Salvation. It was one of theſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46819:18"/> profane Viſions St. <hi>Brigit</hi> pretended to have had, and which <hi>F. Craſſet</hi> hath muſtered up afreſh, to the intent you ſhould not think thoſe Opinions were at all altered ſince thoſe days, 1370. <hi>Sinners</hi> (ſays he) <hi>being her Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Part 1. tr. 1. qu. 10. p. 77.</note> 
               <hi>make up her Crown and Glory, and 'tis for that ſhe loves them, with the tenderneſs and ſweet compaſſion of a Mother, let them be never ſo wicked, as a Mother pittieth her Children, though they have loſt their ſences, and are become mad;</hi> and this is what ſhe has revealed to St. <hi>Brigit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Brig. Revel. book 6. c. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Know Thou</hi> (quoth the Mother to the Daughter) <hi>my deareſt Child, that there is no Man in the World ſo lewd and curs'd of God, that is entirely forſaken of him whilſt he lives; no Sinner ſo deſperate, but may return, and find mercy with him, provided he have recourſe to Me.</hi> St. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> is of the ſame mind, and expreſſes himſelf in theſe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table words: <hi>O</hi> Mary, <hi>be a Man never ſo miſerable a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, you have the ſoft compaſſions of a Mother for him; you embrace him, and hug him cloſe in your boſom, and never will forſake him, till you have reconcil'd him to his formidable Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis with deſign of perſuading us to believe theſe comfortable Truths, that F. <hi>Craſſet</hi> muſters up a whole Chapter of Examples of the wickedeſt Men that poſſibly can be, that yet have been ſaved, by preſerving their <note place="margin">Ubi ſupra. pag. 86.</note> devotion for the Bleſſed Virgin, amidſt all their impieties, entire. Such a one is that of <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Adanus,</hi> a City of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> who having been depos'd of his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaconry, for no great good, gave himſelf over to the Devil, for ſpite and anger, by the help and means of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Magician whom he ſerved. He renounced <hi>Mary</hi> and her Son, and gave the Devil a Scroll ſigned with his own Hand; after which he became intolerably deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and mad for what he had done: But in theſe Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Mind and Soul, a glimpſe or ray of hope appeared
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46819:19"/> to him, that Bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> could deliver him from this evil, and ſtraightways thereupon he goes to her Church, and proſtrates himſelf before her Image: Which failed him not at this time of need, but reconciled him to God, and forced the Devil to give him back his Bonds again.</p>
            <p>To this, F. <hi>Craſſet</hi> thinks ſit to add ſuch another, <note place="margin">Pag. 90. part 1.</note> taken from <hi>Caeſarius;</hi> of a young <hi>Gaſcoign</hi> Soldier, who after he had waſted all he had in the World, gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to <hi>Satan,</hi> and renounced <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> but do whatever the Devil could, he could not be brought to renounce his Mother, and this obtained his Pardon for that horrible Crime; down he threw himſelf before the Image of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which had the Image of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in her arms, and heard this Dialogue between them. The Virgins Image ſaid, <hi>O my ſweet Son, have mercy on this Man:</hi> The Son's Image anſwered, <hi>Why Mother, what would you have me do with this Wretch, that hath renounced Me?</hi> After this, the young Man ſaw the Bleſſed Virgin (that is to ſay, her Image) proſtrate herſelf to little <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and demand again his Pardon, whom <hi>Jeſus</hi> lovingly took up, (and 'twas very much for a Child of his big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,) and ſaid to her, <hi>I never yet refuſed my Mother any thing ſhe ask'd; I grant it for your ſake, and yours alone.</hi> Would one believe, that a Jeſuit ſhould have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to furbiſh up ſuch ridiculous things as theſe, at this time of day, in ſuch an Age as ours? I had often heard this Story told by Proteſtants, to ſhame the Papiſts; but I never thought it would have been produced at this time, by a Renowned Jeſuit, in honour of their Religion, and that too in <hi>Paris,</hi> the moſt frequented City in the whole World. But to put you paſt all doubting of this Truth, F. <hi>Craſſet</hi> tells us, that <hi>Caeſarius</hi> ſays, that this very <hi>Gaſcoign</hi> was alive in his time, 1222. and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was more ſure, nor better atteſted, than this famous
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46819:19"/> Story. And for the credit of <hi>Caeſarius,</hi> the ſame good Father tells us, he was of the Order of <hi>Ciſtercians,</hi> and lived above four hundred years ago, and was, as <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themius</hi> the Abbot tells us, a very Learned, and a very <note place="margin">Pag. 105.</note> Honeſt Man, and one that ſtuck to his rule very cloſe. You may judge (ſays he) of the ſincerity and credit of this Man, by what he ſays in his Preface to his own Works, <hi>God is my Witneſs</hi> (cries he) <hi>that I am not the Inventer of any thing I have reported in my Dialogues.</hi> And who alive can help believing him, after this Proteſtation? Therefore take, in ſhort, another Story of <hi>Caeſarius</hi>'s tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, of one <hi>Beatrix</hi> a Servant in a Convent, who being debauch'd by a Prieſt, got out of the Convent, and lived in a Bawdy-houſe fifteen years, during all which time, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> took her ſhape, and conſtantly ſupplied her place; ſo that no body perceiv'd her abſence, and her Reputation ſuffered nothing all the while; and all this, becauſe ſhe had, as ſhe was going out, prayed to the Virgin, and (giving her the Keys of the Convent into her hand) had ſaid, <hi>Madam, I have ſerved you as devoutly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Caeſarius l. 7. c. 35.</note> 
               <hi>as I poſſibly could; I give you here your Keys again, and am able no longer to withſtand the temptations of the Fleſh.</hi> This tends to the ſame end with all the reſt, namely, to let you underſtand, that, break God's Commands, or do <note place="margin">Craſſ. p. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whatever you pleaſe, ſerve but the Bleſſed Virgin, and all is well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeſwar,</hi> another of F. <hi>Craſſet</hi>'s great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <note place="margin">Stell. Coronae. l. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> tells us, there was a certain Woman that plaid the Whore with a Neighbor's Husband of hers, whoſe Wife finding his roguery out, pray'd to the Virgin to confound that wicked Creature that had debauch'd her Husband from her Bed; but it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound, that this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Harlot had ſtill the grace, every day, to ſay ſeven <hi>Ave Maria</hi>'s, and therefore the Virgins Image anſwered
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46819:20"/> the complaining Wife, and ſaid, <hi>She of whom thou ſpeakeſt, offers me Praiſes that are very agreeable to me, and whilſt ſhe does ſo, I aſſure you Miſtreſs I can never hurt her, but on the contrary, will preſerve her from diſgrace; however I promiſe you, I'll ſee and convert her.</hi> And this is the way to Proſelyte to the Virgin, thoſe who trample God's Commandments under foot.</p>
            <p>If you would have any more Stories, to prove that the Worſhip of the Virgin ſeparate from that of God, is a ſure way to Salvation, you may find them, in great <note place="margin">Craſſet. p. 94.</note> plenty, in Father <hi>Craſſet.</hi> There you may ſee the Virgin keeping them, that keep not God's Commands; and how a Bird having learn'd to cry <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and being ſeized on by a Hawk, ſcream'd out but <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and the ravenous Hawk immediately left her. And likewiſe, how the Devil, being in the Air, and ſpying a Chriſtian that was not upon his guard, came ſwooping down upon him, like a Bird of Prey; but as ſoon as he heard him pronounce, and devoutly call upon the Name of <hi>Mary,</hi> he was fain to pull in his horns (I meant his talons) and be gone. There you ſhall ſee her taking a great deal of pains to raiſe from the dead, Rogues that had liv'd in nothing elſe but wickedneſs, &amp; died without repentance; only to give them leiſure to Confeſs, and do ſome trifling Penances, and then again depart in peace. It is the ſame Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> that tells from <hi>Surius,</hi> the Hiſtory of a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> called <hi>Andrew,</hi> ſo inſufferably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd, that he bore no token or mark of Chriſtianity upon him, but that he was an Admirer of St. <hi>Caeſarion</hi> Martyr: As <hi>Andrew</hi> lived, ſo he died like a Reprobate, without any tokens of Repentance; but at the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Caeſarion,</hi> he aroſe from the dead to Confeſs, and do Penance, and returned from whence he came</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46819:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pelbart</hi> of <hi>Temeſwar</hi> (that never ſticks at any thing) tells us of a Robber on the High-way, (that uſed nevertheleſs to Faſt every <hi>Saturday</hi> in Honour to the Virgin) who at laſt being caught in the Fact, was Beheaded on the ſpot; his Head in falling from his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, cried out thrice, <hi>Confeſſion, Confeſſion, Confeſſion,</hi> upon which they fetch'd a Prieſt, who came and ſet his Head again upon his Shoulders, to whom the Thief reported, that as ſoon as his Head was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut off, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils had ſeiſed on his Soul to drag it into Hell, but that the Virgin hindred them, not permitting the Soul and Body quite to ſeparate, till he was Confeſs'd; and that he had obtained this Grace, for Faſting every <hi>Saturday</hi> to her Honour: And this ſerves to ſupport two Articles of Popery, the Invocation of the Virgin, and the neceſſity of Confeſſion. But if we will not believe <hi>Pelbart,</hi> nor Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> neither will we Hereticks be perſuaded, that a Rogue roſe from the dead.</p>
            <p>In the ſame place, you read how that the Soul of a Soldier kill'd in Fight, in the Service of the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> continued in his Body many years after the Fleſh was rotten and worn off. The Bleſſed Virgin not permitting the Soul to part before Confeſſion, becauſe he had been all his Life time Her peculiar Servant. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Miracle there is, of which <hi>Pelbart</hi> himſelf was an Eye-witneſs. A certain wicked Villain fell into the <hi>Danube,</hi> and was under water three days, where he heard a Voice ſay to him, Thou deſerveſt well, O Wretch, to loſe thy Life, and be Condemn'd for ever for thy Sin but becauſe thou art a Servant to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> thou ſhalt be delivered from this danger, that thou may'ſt go and be Confeſſed; and up he came, though he could not Swim a ſtroke, and came and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd to <hi>Pelbart</hi> himſelf, who tells you this Story. <hi>'Twas</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:46819:21"/> 
               <hi>from the Man his own ſelf</hi> (ſays Father Craſſet) <hi>that this Religious</hi> Pelbart <hi>heard this Hiſtory; and you muſt either believe this Penitent was an Impoſtor and Cheat,</hi> (and I pray take heed of wronging ſuch a Pickled Youth) <hi>or elſe that</hi> Pelbart <hi>was a wicked Man, and took delight to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Page 135.</note> 
               <hi>impoſe upon the belief of the ſoveraign High Prieſt of</hi> Rome, <hi>(to whom he dedicated his Works) and all the Faithful. Or elſe you muſt believe this Story for a certain truth, and conſequently that the Virgin does preſerve ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Servants from everlaſting Damnation, after Death.</hi> And in the ſame Page, this worthy <hi>Jeſuit</hi> ſays, That <hi>Caeſarius</hi> the <hi>Ciſtercian,</hi> that lived about 400. years ſince, and made 12. Books of Dialogues upon Miracles and Apparitions in his time, ſets down many Examples of this nature; how Dead men were ſaved from Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by the Virgins means, obtaining Grace for them, to return to Life again to do ſome Penance.</p>
            <p>If I would drain thoſe Springs (as Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> does) of <hi>Pelbart, Caeſarius, Bernardin de Buſtis, Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Bellovicenſis,</hi> St. <hi>Antonine</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> and the reſt, I could make a monſtrous great Volume of theſe Fables, that tend to the eſtabliſhing the neceſſity of Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Bleſſed Virgin, but this ſmall number drawn from Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> is as good as if I had heaped up all together, with a great deal of Pains and Trouble.</p>
            <p>For by this, we Proteſtants may ſee, how far we are to truſt thoſe <hi>Catholick Doctors,</hi> who would have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, their Service and Religion has for many years laſt paſt, been cleanſed and purified from all theſe vain and idle Popular Superſtitions. When Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Jeſuit, (though Monſieur <hi>Arnaud</hi> call him the <hi>Wretched Jeſuit Craſſet).</hi> A Jeſuit, I ſay, in the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> where Popery is moſt refin'd; in the Face of <hi>Monſieur,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and other Catholicks,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46819:21"/> averſe from the vulgar Superſtitions. When he, I ſay again, renews and revives theſe Silly and Impertinent Fables, with the approbation of his Society, his Arch-Biſhop, and his King. And if the great Man at <hi>Rome,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Of Louis le Grand.</note> ſhould in a good Humour, think fit to ſay, this Book of Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> is compoſed with <hi>ſo much Learning, in ſuch a Method, and with ſuch a Diſcretion, as is proper to inſtruct the Readers clearly in few words, and to extort even from the unwilling (ſuch as</hi> Monſieur de Meaux, <hi>and</hi> Monſieur Arnaud) <hi>a confeſſion of the Catholick Faith.</hi> (In this point) If he, I ſay, ſhould but ſay thus much, I would fain know-why it would not be as Authentick a Book, as the <hi>Catholick Expoſition</hi> of <hi>Monſieur de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> And are we (in good earneſt) ſecure, it never will be ſo? Will a better Friend to the Jeſuits, never poſſeſs that Chair? And if there do, may he not do as much for ſuch a Book as this of Father <hi>Craſſets,</hi> as the preſent Pope has done for <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi>'s? And muſt the Faith of Chriſt be at ſuch uncertainties? This ſurely is not building on a Rock, but on the Sand, that every Wave can waſh away at pleaſure. For if every Pope can make an Expoſition of the Catholick Faith, Authentical, (And if every one cannot, how can any one?) I do not ſee but we may have as many ſeveral Faiths, as there are Caſualties and Diſeaſes in the Weekly Bill.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:46819:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Tho. Newborough, <hi>at the</hi> Star <hi>in St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Travels of Monſieur de <hi>Thevenot</hi> into the <hi>Levant,</hi> in Three Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Into I. <hi>Turkey. II. Perſia. III.</hi> The <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>R. Manlii, <hi>Commentaria de Rebellione Anglicana ab Anno 1640. uſque ad Annum 1685. Pars Prima.</hi> Octa.</p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe with Notes, and a Preface on the Sixth Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> ſhewing that there is neither good Rerſon nor ſufficient Authority, to ſuppoſe that the Euchariſt is diſcourſed of in that Chapter, much leſs to infer the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation from it. Quarto.</p>
            <p>Wholeſome Advices from the Bleſſed Virgin to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Worſhippers. Written by one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion.</p>
            <p>Humanity and Charity of Chriſtians. A Sermon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the <hi>Suffolk</hi> Feaſt, <hi>November,</hi> 30. 1686. by <hi>W. Claget.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>The Preſent State of the Controverſie between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46819:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
